Jedediah Hotchkiss Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Jedediah Hotchkiss Papers 1835-1908 (bulk 1875-1898)
MSS26526
Hotchkiss, Jedediah, 1828-1899
20,000 items
74 containers
29.6 linear feet
61 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Confederate army officer, topographical and mining engineer, and historian. Correspondence, diaries, notebooks, subject files, writings, financial papers, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous printed material relating principally to Hotchkiss's service with the Confederate army as a topographical engineer in Virginia and his involvement with various land and mining schemes in West Virginia, especially the Gauley Coal Company, Guyandot Coal Land Association, and North Flat-Top Land Association. Includes genealogical papers relating to the Hotchkiss and Beecher families, copies of William Barton Rogers's notebooks for his geological survey of Virginia, and papers of Hotchkiss's wife, Sara Anne Comfort Hotchkiss.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allan, William, 1837-1889--Correspondence.; Beecher family.; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893--Correspondence.; Chandler, William E. (William Eaton), 1835-1917--Correspondence.; Dabney, Robert Lewis, 1820-1898--Correspondence.; Daniel, John W. (John Warwick), 1842-1910--Correspondence.; Early, Jubal Anderson, 1816-1894--Correspondence.; Elkins, Stephen B. (Stephen Benton), 1841-1911--Correspondence.; Gordon, John Brown, 1832-1904--Correspondence.; Hotchkiss family.; Hotchkiss, Jedediah, 1828-1899.; Hotchkiss, Sara Anne Comfort. Sara Anne Comfort Hotchkiss papers.; Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863--Correspondence.; LeConte, Joseph, 1823-1901--Correspondence.; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905--Correspondence.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870--Correspondence.; Mahone, William, 1826-1895--Correspondence.; McClure, S. S. (Samuel Sidney), 1857-1949--Correspondence.; McGuire, Hunter, 1835-1900--Correspondence.; Moody, Dwight Lyman, 1837-1899--Correspondence.; Pelham, John, 1838-1863--Correspondence.; Rogers, William Barton, 1804-1882. William Barton Rogers notebooks. 1835-1841.; Stuart, Jeb, 1833-1864--Correspondence.; Tucker, Henry St. George, 1853-1932--Correspondence.; Wise, Henry A. (Henry Alexander), 1806-1876--Correspondence.
Organizations
Confederate States of America. Army.; Gauley Coal Company.; Guyandot Coal Land Association.; North Flat-Top Land Association.
Subjects
Coal mines and mining--West Virginia.; Geology--Virginia.; Land companies--West Virginia.; Land use, Rural--West Virginia.; Military topography--Virginia.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Maps.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Maps.
Titles
Jedediah Hotchkiss Papers at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Army officers, Confederate.; Civil engineers.; Historians.
Provenance
The papers of Jedediah Hotchkiss, topographical and mining engineer, Confederate army officer, and historian, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1948. A small addition to the papers was purchased in 1958.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some maps have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. Photographs and other pictorial material have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Jedediah Hotchkiss Papers. Artifacts have been transferred to the Smithsonian Institution.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Jedediah Hotchkiss are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on sixty-one reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The papers of Jedediah Hotchkiss are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000034.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1828, Nov. 30 Born, Windsor, Broome County, N.Y.
1846 Graduated from Windsor Academy, New Windsor, N.Y.
1846 1847 Taught school, Lykens Valley, Pa.
1847 Walking tour, Cumberland Valley of Maryland and Pennsylvania and Shenandoah Valley, Va. Tutored in home of Daniel Forrer, Luray, Va. Founded Mossy Creek Academy, Augusta County, Va.
1853 Married Sara Anne Comfort
1858 Resigned as headmaster of Mossy Creek Academy, Augusta County, Va., and organized Loch Willow School for Boys at Churchville, Augusta County, Va.
1861 Reported for military duty as topographical engineer with the Army of Northwest Virginia near Parkersburg, Va. Engaged in mapping operations in vicinity of Rich Mountain, W. Va.
1862 Assigned as topographical engineer with Stonewall Jackson's staff near Woodstock, Va.; began mapping Shenandoah Valley from Potomac River to Lexington, Va. Guided Jeb Stuart's troops from Sharpsburg to Shepherdstown, Va.
1862, Dec. Staff duty at Fredericksburg, Va.
1862 1863 In winter quarters with Stonewall Jackson at Moss Neck, Va.
1863, Apr May Night reconnaissance and mapping operations for Chancellorsville; assigned to staff of Richard Ewell after death of Stonewall Jackson,
1863, July Observed troop movements from Seminary Ridge at Gettysburg, Pa.
1864, Mar. May Engaged in mapping duties during Wilderness Campaign and Second Cold Harbor
1864, Oct. Drew maps for Cedar Creek engagement against Philip Sheridan
1864 1865 In winter quarters at Staunton, Va.
1865 Paroled in Staunton, Va. Organized “select school for sons of fellow soldiers,” Churchville, Va. Established office as mining engineer, Staunton, Va.
1867 Published with William Allan The Battle-Fields of Virginia. Chancellorsville... New York: D. Van Nostrand
1870 1871 Acting superintendent of schools, Augusta County, Va.
1872 1875 Spent winters in England and Scotland
1873 Began survey of Great Flat-Top Coal Range in West Virginia
1876 Published Virginia; a Geographical and Political Summary, Richmond, Va.: R. F. Walker, Superintendent of Public Printing
1877 Published Hotchkiss' Geography of Virginia, Richmond, Va.: A. Hoen
1878 Appointed expert special agent of the census for Virginia
1880 Began six-year publication of The Virginias, a periodical promoting the state's resources
1882 Purchased large coal tract on Cabin Creek, Kanawha Valley, W. Va.
1884 Served as Virginia commissioner at World's Industrial and Cotton Centennial Exposition, New Orleans, La. Ran as independent Congressional candidate from 10th District of Virginia
1893 Served as judge for mining exhibits at World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill.
1894 Headed antisaloon campaign, Staunton, Va.
1899, Jan. 17 Died, Staunton, Va.
1899 Posthumous publication of Virginia, [Atlanta]: Confederate Publishing Company, Vol. 3 of Confederate Military History
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jedediah Hotchkiss (1828-1899) span the years 1835-1908, with the bulk of the material dating from 1875 to 1898. The papers reflect his varied activities as a student, geologist, lecturer, school teacher, engineer, soldier, and historian. Hotchkiss's Civil War diaries, notebooks, and journals describe troop movements and battles and reveal a topographer's keen eye for the physical lay of the land. In addition to the original diaries, there are handwritten and typewritten copies or extracts which either vary somewhat from the originals or contain additional information.
Some of Hotchkiss's most informative letters are to his wife, Sara Comfort Hotchkiss, and his brother, Nelson Hotchkiss, during his military duty, 1861-1865. These letters, with variant copies, are in the Family Correspondence series. Other family correspondence includes Hotchkiss's letters to his wife and children, 1872-1875, while he was touring England and correspondence of Sara Hotchkiss, 1853-1903.
The General Correspondence series, the largest in the collection, includes personal and business correspondence, many of which relate to Hotchkiss's involvement with various land and mining ventures in West Virginia, particularly with the Gauley Coal Company, the Guyandot Coal Land Association, and the North Flat-Top Land Association. Between 1875 and 1899, much of the correspondence is concerned with details of Civil War engagements and the publication of Hotchkiss's books. He corresponded frequently with former staff officers of Stonewall Jackson, such as William Allan and Hunter McGuire. There is also correspondence with Jubal Anderson Early, John Brown Gordon, and Fitzhugh Lee. Other correspondents include James Gillespie Blaine, William E. Chandler, Robert Lewis Dabney, John W. Daniel, Stephen B. Elkins, Stonewall Jackson, Joseph LeConte, Robert E. Lee, William Mahone, S. S. McClure, Dwight Lyman Moody, John Pelham, Jeb Stuart, Henry St. George Tucker, and Henry A. Wise.
The Subject File reflects Hotchkiss's entrepreneurial and scholarly interests and includes drafts and notes of his writings and newspaper clipping files on diverse subjects. The Subject File also includes copies of William Barton Rogers's notebooks concerning his geological survey of Virginia, 1835-1841. There is no material in this collection associated with Hotchkiss's political activities as an independent Congressional candidate in 1884.
The Miscellany series contains genealogical records of the Hotchkiss and Beecher families. This series also contains financial records in the form of account books, canceled checks, bank notes, and bills and receipts.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Diaries, 1845-1899
Notebooks, 1866-1893
Family Correspondence, 1853-1903
General Correspondence, 1846-1899
Subject File, circa 1835-1899
Writings File, circa 1846-1899
Miscellany, circa 1846-1908
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 17, 917
- Diaries, 1845-1899 (Box 1-5, Reel 1-3)
  Bound diaries and loose diary pages, with transcripts and extracts of diary entries.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1845, July 4-Sept. 23 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1846, June 19-Sept. 10
  - 1847, Apr. 26.- Aug. 2
  - 1847, Aug. 3-1848, Mar. 3
  - 1848, Mar. 5-Apr. 23
  - 1848, Apr. 16-May 28
  - 1850 (weather and flower tables)
  - 1851, July 1-Dec. 30 (with miscellaneous notes, 1852-1853)
  - 1851 (almanac/notebook)
  - 1859, June 13-Nov. 26
  - 1861, June 26-Sept. 17
  - 1861 (miscellaneous fragments); Mar. 14-May 7; 1862, Oct. 6-19
  - 1861, June 15-1862, May 16 (extracts)
  - 1861, June 15-1862, May 24 (extracts)
  - 1861, Dec. 9-1862, Mar. 31 (extracts)
  - 1861, Dec. 14-31
  - 1862, Mar. 27-May 19 (extracts/variants)
  - 1862, May 4-Dec. 14
  - 1862, May 20-Dec. 16 (extracts) (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 1862, Mar. 10-May 12 (extracts)
  - 1863, Jan. 1-Nov. 28
  - 1863, Apr. 29-Nov. 28 (extracts)
  - 1863, Oct. 24-1864, Apr. 30
  - 1864, May-June (miscellaneous notes)
  - 1864, May 1-Dec. 23 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - 1864, Nov. 9-1865, May 8 (extracts)
  - 1861, June 15-1865, Dec. 23 (extracts) (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 1870 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - 1871
  - 1872
  - 1874, July 14- Sept. 15
  - 1874-1875 (miscellaneous fragments)
  - 1874-1876 (miscellaneous fragments)
  - 1876
  - 1876-1877 (miscellaneous fragments) (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - 1878-1890 (diary/notebook miscellany)
  - 1880 (miscellaneous fragments)
  - 1881
  - 1882 (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - 1884 (miscellaneous fragments)
  - 1889
  - 1890
  - 1891
  - 1892
  - 1893
  - 1894
  - 1896
  - 1898
  - 1899
- Notebooks, 1866-1893 (Box 6, Reel 4)
  Mining field notes, work logs, and coal analyses.
  - General (Box 6, Reel 4)
    - 1866, Oct.-Nov. (“Journal of Operations, etc. Top. Eng. Office”)
    - 1869 (fragments)
    - 1878 (fragments)
    - 1891-1892
    - 1893
    - Undated (1 of 2)
    - Undated (2 of 2)
  - Geological
    - 1880-1883 (fragments)
    - 1887
    - Undated (1 of 2)
    - Undated (2 of 2)
- Family Correspondence, 1853-1903 (Box 7-8, Reel 4-5)
  Correspondence of Jedediah Hotchkiss, Sara Anne Comfort Hotchkiss, and other members of Hotchkiss family.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein.
  - Hotchkiss, Jedediah (Box 7, Reel 4)
    - To Nelson H. Hotchkiss (brother), 1855
    - To Sara Anne Comfort Hotchkiss (wife)
      - 1861
      - 1862
      - 1863
      - 1864-1865
      - 1870-1875
      - Undated
    - Letterbooks
      - 1861, June 27-1864, Dec. 30, typed copies of letters to Sara A. C. Hotchkiss and Nelson H. Hotchkiss
      - 1861-1864, variant copies of same
  - Hotchkiss, Sara Anne Comfort (Box 8, Reel 5)
    - 1853-1875 ,1885
    - 1899 (1 of 2)
    - 1899 (2 of 2)
    - 1900
    - 1901-1903, undated
  - Howison, Allan M., and Anne Lydia Hotchkiss, letters of condolence upon death of Jedediah Hotchkiss, 1899
  - McCullough, Ellen Hotchkiss, 1874-1875, 1899-1901
  - Miscellany, 1854-1863
- General Correspondence, 1846-1899 (Box 9-32, Reel 5-34)
  Letters sent and received.
  - 1846-1848 (Box 9, Reel 5)
  - 1852-1859
  - 1861
  - 1862
  - 1863
  - 1864
  - 1865
  - 1866
  - 1867
  - 1868
  - 1869 (Box 9, Reel 6)
  - 1870
  - 1871
  - 1872
  - 1873, Jan.-May (Box 10, Reel 6)
  - 1873, June-Dec.
  - 1874
  - 1875
  - 1876
  - 1877
  - 1878
  - 1879
  - 1880 (Box 11, Reel 6)
  - 1881 (Box 11, Reel 7)
  - 1882
  - 1883, Jan.-Mar.
  - 1883, Apr.-Aug.
  - 1883, Sept.-Dec.
  - 1884, Jan.-Aug. (Box 12, Reel 7)
  - 1884, Sept.-Dec.
  - 1885
  - 1886 (Box 12, Reel 8)
  - 1887
  - 1888 (Box 13, Reel 8)
  - 1889, Jan.-June
  - 1889, July-Dec.
  - 1890, Jan.-June
  - 1890, July-Dec.
  - 1891, Jan.-June. (Box 14, Reel 8)
  - 1891, July-Sept.
  - 1891, Oct.-Dec. (Box 14, Reel 9)
  - 1892, Jan.-Mar.
  - 1892, Apr.-June
  - 1892, July-Sept.
  - 1892, Oct.-Dec.
  - 1893, Jan.-Mar. (Box 15, Reel 9)
  - 1893, Apr.-Mar.
  - 1893, June-Apr.
  - 1893, Sept-Oct.
  - 1893, Nov.-Dec.
  - 1894, Jan.-Feb. (Box 15, Reel 10)
  - 1894, Mar.
  - 1894, Apr. (Box 16, Reel 10)
  - 1894, May
  - 1894, June
  - 1894, July
  - 1894, Aug.
  - 1894, Sept.
  - 1894, Oct.
  - 1894, Nov.
  - 1894, Dec.
  - 1895, Jan. (Box 17, Reel 11)
  - 1895, Feb.
  - 1895, Mar.
  - 1895, Apr.
  - 1895, May
  - 1895, June
  - 1895, July
  - 1895, Aug.
  - 1895, Sept. (Box 18, Reel 11)
  - 1895, Oct.
  - 1895, Nov.
  - 1895, Dec. (Box 18, Reel 12)
  - 1896. Jan.
  - 1896, Feb..
  - 1896, Mar.
  - 1896, Apr.
  - 1896, May (Box 19, Reel 12)
  - 1896, June
  - 1896, July
  - 1896, Aug. (Box 19, Reel 13)
  - 1896, Sept. (Box 19, Reel 13)
  - 1896, Oct.
  - 1896, Nov.
  - 1896, Dec.
  - 1897, Jan. 1-15 (Box 20, Reel 13)
  - 1897, Jan. 19-30
  - 1897, Feb.
  - 1897, Mar.
  - 1897, Apr. (Box 20, Reel 14)
  - 1897, May
  - 1897, June
  - 1897, July
  - 1897, Aug. (Box 21, Reel 14)
  - 1897, Sept.
  - 1897, Oct.
  - 1897, Nov.
  - 1897, Dec.
  - 1898, Jan.
  - 1898, Feb.
  - 1898, Mar. (Box 22, Reel 15)
  - 1898, Apr.
  - 1898, May
  - 1898, June
  - 1898, July
  - 1898, Aug.
  - 1898, Sept.
  - 1898, Oct.-Nov. (Box 23, Reel 15)
  - 1898, Nov. (Box 23, Reel 16)
  - 1898, Dec. (Box 23, Reel 16)
  - 1899, Jan.
  - Undated (Box 23, Reel 16)
  - Cut signatures, undated
  - Miscellaneous fragments
  - Letterbooks (Box 24, Reel 16)
    - 1873, Mar. 7-1873, Apr. 9
    - 1873, Mar. 7-1873, Apr. 9 (Box 24, Reel 17)
    - 1873, May 21-1881, May 9
    - 1874-1879, 1886-1887 (Box 24, Reel 18)
    - 1874, Sept. 3-1895, Feb. 8
    - 1875, Apr. 9-1876, Jan. 3 (Box 25, Reel 18)
    - 1875, Feb. 20-1876, Mar. 22 (Box 25, Reel 19)
    - 1876, May 9-1879, Feb. 4 (Box 25, Reel 19)
    - 1879, Feb. 5-1879, July 31
    - 1879, July 30-1882, Sept. 14
    - 1880-1882 (census enumerator's book)
    - 1881, May 9-1882, Dec. 28 (Box 25, Reel 20)
    - 1881, Oct. 8-1882, June 5
    - 1882, Sept. 18-1887, Aug. 17 (Box 26, Reel 20)
    - 1883-1886 (Box 26, Reel 21)
    - 1884, Sept. 19-1885, Feb. (Box 26, Reel 22)
    - 1885, Dec. 28-1887, Aug. 26 (Box 27, Reel 22)
    - 1885, Dec. 28-1887, Aug. 26 (Box 27, Reel 23)
    - 1887, Sept. 5-1889, Sept. 7 (Box 27, Reel 24)
    - 1887, Sept. 5-1889, Sept. 7 (Box 27, Reel 25)
    - 1887, Aug. 29-1891, Apr. 16 (Box 28, Reel 25)
    - 1888-1891 (Box 28, Reel 26)
    - 1889, Dec. 19-1891, Aug. 1
    - 1889, Nov. 9-1892, Apr. 16 (Box 29, Reel 27)
    - 1892, Apr. 16 - Aug. 13 (Box 29, Reel 28)
    - 1890, Dec. 20-1892, Feb. 22 (Box 29, Reel 28)
    - 1892-1894, Guyandot Coal Land Association (Box 30, Reel 29)
    - 1892-1894 (1 of 2) (Box 30, Reel 30)
    - 1892-1894 (2 of 2) (Box 30, Reel 31)
    - 1893-1895 (1 of 2) (Box 30, Reel 31)
    - 1893-1895 (2 of 2) (Box 31, Reel 31)
    - 1893-1895 (Box 31, Reel 32)
    - 1895-1896 (Box 31, Reel 33)
    - 1895-1896, Virginias Railroad Co.
    - 1896-1898, “War Book,” correspondence concerning Stonewall Jackson (Box 32, Reel 34)
    - 1896-1898, Virginias Railroad Co.
- Subject File, circa 1835-1899 (Box 33-47, Reel 35-44)
  Correspondence, maps, tracings, sketches, notes, printed matter, and legal documents.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of company or subject of research.
  - Antietam, Battle of (Box 33, Reel 35)
  - Basic City Mining and Manufacturing Co.
  - Bland County lands
  - Bland County Land Improvement, Development, and Transportation Co.
  - Cabin lands (1 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (2 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (3 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (4 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (5 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (6 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (7 of 8)
  - Cabin lands (8 of 8)
  - Catawba Furnace property, 1879 (Box 34, Reel 36)
  - Cedar Creek, Battle of, 1864
  - Cedar Run, Battle of, 1862
  - Central Coking Coal Land Association, 1887
  - Chancellorsville, Battle of, 1863
  - Chesapeake, Shendun, and Western Railroad Co., 1891
  - Chesapeake and Western Railroad Co., 1894
  - Chicago Coking Coal Land Association, circa 1896
  - Coal production, circa 1894
  - Confederate veterans, 1895-1896
  - Elkhorn lands, undated
  - Esteline Furnace lands, undated
  - Flat-Top Range lands, 1893-1898 (1 of 4) (Box 35, Reel 36)
  - Flat-Top Range lands, 1893-1898 (2 of 4)
  - Flat-Top Range lands, 1893-1898 (3 of 4)
  - Flat-Top Range lands, 1893-1898 (4 of 4)
  - Fredericksburg, Battle of, 1862
  - Gallatin Coal and Land Co., undated
  - Gauley Coal Land Association, 1890-1897 (1 of 4) (Box 36, Reel 37)
  - Gauley Coal Land Association, 1890-1897 (2 of 4)
  - Gauley Coal Land Association, 1890-1897 (3 of 4)
  - Gauley Coal Land Association, 1890-1897 (4 of 4)
  - Glenmore Iron Estate, undated
  - Grottoes Co., 1891 (1 of 2)
  - Grottoes Co., 1891 (2 of 2)
  - Guy Run Iron lands, 1873
  - Guyandot Coal Land Association, 1889-1895 (1 of 6) (Box 37, Reel 37)
  - Guyandot Coal Land Association, 1889-1895 (2 of 6)
  - Guyandot Coal Land Association, 1889-1895 (3 of 6)
  - Guyandot Coal Land Association, 1889-1895 (4 of 6)
  - Guyandot Coal Land Association, 1889-1895 (5 of 6)
  - Guyandot Coal Land Association, 1889-1895 (6 of 6)
  - Hale Pavement Co., 1886-1888 (1 of 5) (Box 38, Reel 38)
  - Hale Pavement Co., 1886-1888 (2 of 5)
  - Hale Pavement Co., 1886-1888 (3 of 5)
  - Hale Pavement Co., 1886-1888 (4 of 5)
  - Hale Pavement Co., 1886-1888 (5 of 5)
  - Harman, John A., circa 1862 (Box 38, Reel 39)
  - Hinton, New River, and Western Railroad Co., undated
  - Imboden, John D., 1862-1863
  - “Index to papers in boxes,” circa 1896
  - Jackson, Stonewall, 1892 (Box 39, Reel 39)
  - Jackson, Stonewall, staff officers, 1861, 1893 (1 of 2)
  - Jackson, Stonewall, staff officers, 1861, 1893 (2 of 2)
  - Krise Iron Co., undated
  - Lee, Robert E., 1865
  - Leigh, Benjamin Watkins, undated
  - Malvern Hill, Battle of, 1862
  - Manassas, 2nd Battle of, 1862 (1 of 2)
  - Manassas, 2nd Battle of, 1862 (2 of 2)
  - Maps, miscellany
    - "Plot of D. Ferrer's Meadow ...", circa 1848
    - Map of battlefields, Civil War, undated
    - Maps, post-1865
    - Maps and sketches, circa 1861-1865
    - Maps, post-1865
    - Maps, lists and notes, undated
    - Maps, post-1865 (mining etc.)
  - McDowell, Battle of, 1862 (Box 40, Reel 40)
  - Mining and Manufacturers Association of the Virginias, 1885
  - Morris, Robert, survey, undated (1 of 2)
  - Morris, Robert, survey, undated (2 of 2)
  - National Express and Transportation Co., suit, circa 1885-1894
  - Norfolk and Western Railroad, undated
  - Peck land deal, circa 1873-1875
  - Potomac and Ohio Railroad, circa 1895
  - Valley iron ore lands, 1891-1893
  - Presbyterian Church, 1891-1895
  - Rich, Patch, and Purgatory iron lands, undated
  - Roaring Run Iron Works and Estate, 1882-1888 (Box 41, Reel 40)
  - Selma lands, William Easton deal, 1875 (1 of 2)
  - Selma lands, William Easton deal, 1875 (2 of 2)
  - Stockton coal lands, undated
  - Stoneman's Raid, 1863, May
  - Swan lands and estate, undated
  - Swecker iron property, 1887
  - United New Jersey Railroad and Canal Co., undated
  - Valley Railroad Co., 1870
  - Virginia geological survey by William Barton Rogers, letterpress and carbon copies of drafts, 1835-1841
    - Biographical material and notes
    - Catalog of notebooks
    - Notebooks, circa 1835-1840 (Box 41, Reel 40)
      - Nos. 1-7 (incomplete)
      - No. 1 (Box 42, Reel 41)
      - No. 2
      - No. 3
      - No. 4
      - No. 5
      - No. 6
      - No. 7
      - Nos. 8-12, incomplete working draft
      - No. 8.F (Box 43, Reel 41)
      - No. 8
      - No. 9
      - No. 10
      - Nos. 11-12
      - No. 13
      - Nos. 14-15
      - No. 17
      - Nos. 18-19
      - Nos. 20-21
      - Nos. 22-23 (Box 44, Reel 42)
      - Nos. 24-25
      - Nos. 26-27
      - Nos. 28-29
      - No. 30
      - Nos. 31-34
      - Nos. 35-38
      - Nos. 39-40
      - Nos. 41-44
      - Nos. 45-48
      - Nos. 50-53
      - Nos. 54-55
      - Nos. 56-58
      - No. 59
      - No. 60 (Box 45, Reel 42)
      - No. 61
    - Rodgers, William Barton (Box 45, Reel 42)
      - Report of the Progress of the Geological Survey... (1839)
      - A Reprint of Annual Papers and Other Papers on the Geology of Virginia (1884)
    - Miscellaneous copies of correspondence, 1838-1841 (Box 45, Reel 43)
  - Virginia Geological Survey, 1898 (Box 46, Reel 43)
  - Virginia Hot Springs Co., circa 1892
  - Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, Va., 1868
  - Virginia Plaster Co., suit, circa 1890-1897 (Box 46, Reel 43)
  - Virginia, Shendun lands, 1895-1898
  - Virginia statistical information, undated
  - Virginia, Staunton, 1894, undated (1 of 2)
  - Virginia, Staunton, 1894, undated (2 of 2)
  - Virginia, University of, Charlottesville, Va., undated
  - Virginias Internal Improvememt Co., undated
  - Virginias Railroad Co., 1895-1896, undated (1 of 2)
  - Virginias Railroad Co., 1895-1896, undated (2 of 2)
  - Washington College, Lexington, Va. (now Washington and Lee University), 1868 (1 of 2) (Box 47, Reel 43)
  - Washington College, Lexington, Va. (now Washington and Lee University), 1868 (2 of 2)
  - West Virginia Geological Survey, 1898
  - West Virginia statistical information, circa 1893
  - World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1893 (1 of 3)
  - World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1893 (2 of 3)
  - World's Columbian Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1893 (3 of 3) (Box 47, Reel 44)
  - World's Industrial and Cotton Centennial Exposition, New Orleans, La., 1884
- Writings File, circa 1846-1899 (Box 48-60, Reel 44-51)
  Books, articles, essays, speeches, lectures, book reviews, and notes.
  Arranged in three groups: books, other writings of Hotchkiss, and writings by others.
  - Books by Hotchkiss (Box 48, Reel 44)